knowledge is power
[Music]
adjusting to not having my default be
you know pst time so of course yes yes
yes
uh what what prompted the move if i may
ask
uh well so i'm uh i've been a dj an
audio engineer for the last ten years
and the lockdowns in the the pandemic
situation kind of took away my jobs um
so it just kind of like catapulted this
big series of events of changes in my
life and
had a you know a long-term relationship
that that split away and so i just kind
of looking i'm about 29 now almost 30.
so it's kind of like
let's uh let's go somewhere else let's
check it out
nice i like that you just shuffle the
deck and and
do something different i yes i did more
of that when i was younger i'm 65 now i
i have a feeling i'm i'm much more
uh stationary or stabilized than i was
um but i had some i had some great moves
like that that when i was younger right
right i heard you i was listening to you
on another podcast and you had mentioned
um kind of like a mid-life crisis of
sorts um to where you just kind of like
shifted
you kind of just went went a different
way um yeah that's right yeah yeah i
yeah so there are there are these um
these strange you could say hairpin
curves in life that are interesting to
me um because
we don't normally think of lives as
doing that there's even the extreme
theory that no one changes um
uh yeah we
i'll buy that as long as we also
remember that everybody changes but but
the the hairpin ones are really
interesting to me yeah
how that happens
yeah and then because at the moment it
seems catastrophic and you're like what
am i doing and your whole sense of
identity has just been you know changed
or crumbled or questioned or whatever it
is but then retrospectively you're like
oh yeah of course it was that way you
know
yes
there is that um
i was joking to a friend yesterday that
uh that my adulthood has been um
uh just alternating between midlife
crises and second childhoods
it's not exactly true but it but there's
something to it anyway i like that kind
of self-effacing i like that yeah it
definitely puts the finger on something
there there's something
um well cool man yeah um i'm really
thanks again for uh for working with me
to get this rescheduled i was really
looking forward to this talk and um i've
been kind of like listening to you on
some other podcasts and i was listening
to your talk at google and just like oh
yeah i'm so excited to talk about these
things so fun fun we can talk about
anything what do you like to talk about
a little bit of everything i mean the
a few years back so i actually kind of
um
i i've always been kind of you know
fairly fascinated with just
the edge of ideas and and um
just just like like what we're doing
like like going very meta on kind of
like this whole situation here life um
so but and then a couple years back i
had a lot of uh kind of like mental
health depression kind of
came into this point of wow how do i
better take care of myself what am i
doing incorrectly what's going on like
so i start studying myself i start
studying studying what a self is uh
start studying consciousness
just like through this kind of mental
health journey i got even more
fascinated with um just really like like
selfhood and and studying uh what it is
that we do and why it is that we do it
and why it is that we matter and how and
using your words how does matter uh
how how does matter give rise does that
mattering emerge from matter there's one
more version of it yeah yeah so it's
always matter
all of it really fascinates me yeah ah
great and the and um
most of the literature that deals with
this question what is the self starts at
the level of
humans or maybe animals it starts at the
level of feelings and thoughts
um
but
that's not our approach in fact the guy
the main guy i work with this guy i've
been working with for a quarter century
terence deacon
compares that to trying to understand
hair starting with porcupines
um yes porcupine quills are hair they're
highly evolved and highly specialized
so there's a difference in our approach
and i just think about it before the
podcast started um
that
it's it's on the edge of pretentious to
say it but i'm going to say it i realize
i can actually just say it which is that
um
i'm not like other social scientists or
life scientists um i go back to the
origins now that sounds like some creepy
uh sacred text citation now what i mean
by it is that i'm what i call an
originist which is i'm operating on an
assumption that's in
implied in science but not necessarily
practice and certainly not in
consciousness studies which is that the
prior sciences have to explain what the
later sciences assume
and until they do we don't really know
what we're talking about when we talk
about something like consciousness or
something any of those uh high-level
uh assumptions so
unlike most cognitive science
researchers or even social scientists we
have to start from the chemical origins
of trying
that cells are the only things that try
and we can imagine anything like a self
i can imagine that the river is trying
to get to the sea or the computers
trying to help me out but really when
you look at it we're the only ones that
try and if you want to understand trying
which is a
it's an inescapable concept
in the life and social sciences and an
inapplicable
concept in the in the physical sciences
that is you can never talk about
molecules trying but you have to talk
about living things drying you have to
be able to explain trying from
its origins in chemistry explain no
smoke and mirrors just how did what is
trying and how did it start and actually
that's the reverse of the question how
it started will give you a better sense
of what trying is
oh wow okay so do you see is there is
there a big gap between survival in
trying uh because no actually no
so survival is actually the key to it
and
we're
we're living through a strange period in
the sciences in the in the life and
social sciences and that would include
cognitive science and philosophy and all
that where we uh we think we found the
answer because we got evolution and then
we got dna well dna is not trying you
know this stuff looks like snot if you
take it out of a body and put it on
table looks like it's not okay and it's
not and snot is even more alive than
it's a bunch of chemicals right it's not
about anything for anyone that is trying
to do anything until it's in a living
organism but there's also this
assumption that somehow i mean it's it's
a very strange and loose and not
scientific
concept that somehow a new thing came
into the universe called natural
selection and that somehow started life
now we know that's not the case i mean
we have all these details about how
evolution works and how it has worked in
historically in natural history but we
are still trying to figure out what the
origins of life is so obviously it
doesn't solve the problem the struggle
for existence
is something that darwin assumed he
declared that he had no explanation for
it he assumed the struggle for existence
and then explained how that would
speciate into different
ways of struggling with respect to
different environments that's what he
did and he knew it and people tried to
say didn't you just explain the origins
of life and he said no
i didn't i don't get to say that um
somehow we've forgotten that so
and the struggle for existence this this
is the most fundamental thing which is
that
we have to struggle for our existence
because um
things fall apart it's the second law of
thermodynamics things are max things are
moving towards disorder or getting all
mixed up and we have to keep ourselves
in order so i just started my day out
here and i don't have much schedule but
i do have gen regenerating 240 billion
cells today and i might do that without
feeling it without thinking i have to
run in order to stay in place i have to
hustle to just keep myself alive
and that's true of all organisms so
that's where we we have to explain how
that kind of struggle to self-regenerate
could ever emerge from simple chemistry
not quantum mechanics or anything like
that we don't operate at that level how
it could ever happen by accident that we
would get in the business of
regenerating ourselves faster than we
would otherwise degenerate
yeah wow fascinating okay so how does
your
like your day-to-day work when you're
actually studying this because it's um
perhaps i'm not super familiar with the
the real hard time definition of
philosophy of science or anything like
that but i do see you know science over
here in philosophy over here to me
philosophy is uh just so much more of
the pondering side of things so how do
you how do you take these questions and
actually bring them into science
yeah so uh
i'm working with a scientist and i'm
we debate whether i get to call myself a
scientist or a science writer because of
a way in which we uh an assumption we
make about science um
we think the science scientific
revolution started with um empiricism in
the enlightenment that is the the the
bringing rigor
to trying to figure out to testing
things out against reality so philosophy
was doing a lot of theorizing and then
they said no if you really want to do
this stuff you have to ground it in
experiments
um
so
a lot of people assume and and
scientists do assume that um if you're
not doing experiments you're not a
scientist
but actually i think that there have
been two scientific revolutions so far
and i think we need one more in fact i'm
writing an article about it just now so
the first one was way back with let's
say
pythagoras or uh plato or aristotle it's
bringing rigor to formalism
formalism is all the ability to make
mathematical and logical models
basically manipulating symbols
and doing it for maximum
coherence
coherence means that you're not talking
about both sides of your mouth you're
maintaining consistency
and that was the first scientific
revolution
and
a guy like francis bacon realizes it's
not enough to do that i mean you can
come up with really coherent theories
that have no correspondence to reality
um you know i for example i could say
that everything in the universe is made
from
uh
jello gelatin that's a perfectly
coherent theory
it's or i could more popularly i could
say it's all good
yes it's a perfectly incoherent theory
and yes if you if you define good
broadly enough to include bad sure it's
true you know but
uh but
so he so they realized francis bacon
realized no you gotta you gotta
make this stuff correspond to sense data
so um that's the second scientific
revolution what i think is missing
is a third one which brings rigor to
categorization
and this comes out of some work by a
philosopher out of the
early american philosopher charles
sanders purse who points out that there
are actually three basic kinds of
logical moves deduction induction and
abduction okay abduct so
and i could explain more about that but
but the heart of it is
right now we categorize pretty damn
casually especially on these big
intractable questions like
uh
life and and mind and motivation so if
you talk to a um
if you talk
motivation is the core currency in the
life and social sciences basically
trying and we assume that there's
something inside of an organism that
would have an appetite or a will or
a motivation uh that would trigger some
kind of behavior but if you ask a social
scientist i mean they live and breathe
motivation if you ask them what a
motivation is they can't tell you
they know what a motivation does
and they mostly identify motivations by
their consequences if i see you making
effort
i'll assume that you have a motivation
well to me that's no more rigorous than
saying you have a soul
you can give it you can give it a uh you
can give it a spiritual sounding name or
a technical sounding name doesn't matter
naming is not explaining
so that's so
uh that's where the originism comes in
which is if you really want to
understand a phenomenon you have to
explain what how it emerged from what
preceded it
yeah yeah it is interesting the
assumptions uh that we
assumptions slash leaps that we're like
okay yeah and keep keep going next one
uh
what do you think like the this third
stage of science do you think that we're
at a place where uh you know the the
current rules of science the current
edges of science so to say um are kind
of constraining us from answering
important questions like how do we when
we're going to expand into this um
i don't know next stage that next stage
of science
what are we going to lose from this like
what are we going to have to
to not only lose but but add in um i
understand that's not a species yeah no
no no no that's right it's a good
question um i mostly don't think we have
to add anything we have to remember
something about
the sciences right now they're kind of
multidisciplinary or transdisciplinary
that is that you francis bacon basically
said we're going to send out a search
party and do all this empirical research
and it's going to each each search party
is going to be exploring some patch of
reality and trying to understand what's
going on there and we've been doing that
now for 400 years 350 years um and the
patches have expanded and they have
encroached on each other in delightful
ways so we get this sense that there are
parallels for example between what
animals do and what humans do or i mean
it's all sorts of parallels um
but it's still
it's
it's um
it's trans-disciplinary at best i
actually am arguing that it needs to be
sequi-disciplinary
that is the science is actually are
stacked in order of appearance
we you know the universe is 14 billion
years old and for the first 10 billion
years that's two-thirds of its existence
we see nothing that needs to be
explained in terms of trying nothing i
mean not in this deck of the woods
anyway we haven't seen anything yet man
no doubt it happened elsewhere earlier
or whatever but trying seems to be
something different
from nothing but chemistry that is if
you're playing in science i assume i i
take science to be a campaign to find
natural explanations for all natural
phenomena which means that we can't say
well there's some
magical thing that was added that
explains this thing you can't do that if
you do that for one thing you can't
def you could do it to anything you know
i can explain lightning by the lightning
wanter you know or something like that
the magical invisible unknowable
supernatural lightning wanter so if i
can't do it if i do it anywhere i can't
do it you know i do it everywhere so
science is just that campaign so um
so that means that we have to be able to
explain emergencies with no smoke and
mirrors no no abstractions that an allow
us to smuggle in something
um to explain it
and and so that's what i'm that's what
i'm basically arguing and once we have
explained it we can reduce to it so
there's this idea that you know
all there is in the universe all we ever
see is let's say we we drop it down to
the lowest level subatomic particles or
field forces whatever whatever it is
therefore all explanations have to be
reduced to that or else they don't make
any sense and i'm saying no actually
that's not true i'm an emergent
reductionist which is to say that once
we have really explained
that how
how physical work changes the likeliness
of this happening versus that happening
once we've explained how a phenomenon
emerges
then we are we can reduce to that
explained phenomena
and until then we can't
so
and then in a way that's
that's a standard that
that makes some sense obviously we can't
do it to the pre-einsteinian or
pre-quantum level yet that's not this
season's researchers project
we don't know enough yet to be able to
do that but we at least need to mark
what we don't have explained and we
don't do that very well
in especially cognitive science
so you get so to get to give you know a
quick illustration
in cognitive science the hard problem is
if we are just these cause and effect
mechanisms if animals are basically
mechanisms like machines you know uh or
computers popular notion these days then
how do we explain experience or what
they call qualia the red the feeling of
redness
i call that the made harder problem
um yes if you assume we're nothing but
machines that don't try to do anything
um yeah you're going to have a hell of a
time explaining qualia or experience
from that but that's not where we
started we were trying
if you don't even have an explanation
for what trying is
you're
don't you know don't expect uh much of
explaining consciousness out of
computation you know
and and the same is true with the free
will debate that thing will go on back
and forth the determinant is saying uh
you are nothing but determinist
chemistry um
which is funny because you actually
means that you're not just that it's a
distinctive category of thing and then
the free will people say no obviously
you have will and i'm we're arguing that
it's it's got a kind of autonomy well if
we don't know what will is once again if
we don't know what motivation is from
its origins in chemistry
what are we even talking about you know
it's this unknown quantity that
everybody thinks they know
um but they only know by its
consequences we see willful behavior but
we can't explain we know it happens in
bodies we know it is instantiated in
chemistry but we haven't explained what
it is so that's where our work has been
primarily focused oh and a while ago you
asked how do we do this work
well
yeah sorry for getting off track and for
perhaps having too much coffee i'll just
i'll say this one last thing oh you're
fine i tend to get a little long um but
that's because there's a lot of
different things to hold in the air at
the same time i'm here for it man i love
it okay good so the um
i think that natural philosophy was the
right name for the field and that
science is a great name for it but
actually i think that we should keep in
mind that science is not just testing
things out tests are hell expensive
so that means that what you have to
actually do is prioritize your testing
which means that you're shopping among
interpretations of reality that are
worth testing and not worth testing
so you cannot be a scientist without
engaging in this fundamental
topic of shopping among interpretations
what is the best fitting interpretation
for reality and that tends among
scientists to get the short shrift as if
that's
as if
as if that's not part of science as if
science is just lab tensor testing or as
if you know or as if we leave that to
the philosophers
no we're still all shopping among
interpretations and then we test them
out and i'm arguing that the third
scientific revolution just would
remember that we're a little loose about
our categorization of things like
motivation or will or love
um
so
my approach is uh is a our approach the
one i got by working with terence deacon
is is different from that i
i actually have an explanation for both
junkyards and love
from the origins of life from chemistry
as i have a definition of love that
comes out of
my origins of life explanation and no it
ain't poetry it ain't poetry at all
okay what is it what would you how would
you
explain love well um
so uh
it's doing dedicated work to maintain
something you're dependent upon
um now where you draw the line and start
calling it love which is a feeling we
associate with uh animals and
particularly with humans
that's one thing but if we're talking
about
a certain kind of behavior from its
origins
um
what i mean by dedicated work is of all
the things you could do
you constrain your yourself to certain
work that's actually our explanation for
um
motivation or will or trying anyway that
is i'm not my breakfast my trying is not
my breakfast that breakfast could have
been used for any number of things
including starting a fire that burns
down my house whatever um it tends to do
more damage than not energy gradients
tend to do more damage than not but i am
a constraint that channels that energy
into
effort
to do what to regenerate that constraint
that is i got a to-do list today but
actually the to-do list is a narrowing
of possibilities i could dither all day
but instead i limit what i do all day to
certain things that will enable me to
limit what i do tomorrow
to keep myself going i am actually an
emergent constraint that's what i think
of and when i'm dead that emergent
constraint is this go on as a popped
bubble or a whirlpool from yesterday i
mean that i don't actually think there's
any
i am a limitation on what happens i am
not something added that makes that
happen it's a way that chemical
interactions can actually limit what
happens um so
uh
love would also be that it's doing
dedicated work it's being deliberated
or deliberate that is i'm unliberating
myself i'm saying to be to maintain
access to this thing or to maintain
something i care about i have to do
dedicated work and how do i know that
i'm dependent on it
if you remove it
am i as paul mccartney said suddenly not
half the man i used to be that as you
can tell when something
um has failed to maintain
something that it depends upon because
it becomes degenerate in some ways i
don't mean degenerate in the
psychological or you know i just mean uh
were were hobbled
so this is going on from the very
origins of life um now i want to name it
by another name
i think that love and addiction
refer to the same behavior
the difference is connotation
if i think a relationship is going to
turn out well for someone i'll say
that's love if i think it's not going to
turn out well for them i'm going to say
it's addiction and
and i as a result i i'm busy a lot of my
time
stripping the connotations off of words
for example i would say that i am an
incredibly lucky guy because i happen to
really like my addictions i have some
addictions that i just i just have
killer addictions i love no i don't mean
killer that is i think they're gonna
sustain me as long as possible yeah i
think they're killing them yeah they
maintain me i don't feel like half the
man i used to be or like i'm gonna be
deprived of them i mean of course i am
in the end but uh or in my decline but
anyway boy was that a lot i hope
it was so good i feel like you poked so
many different parts of my uh uh my
brain to to spit out different ideas i
was thinking about um i was thinking
about pan psycho pansys actually do do
you have any uh what's your opinion on
on pan psychics and basically what is it
that matter gives rise to consciousness
or or
matter is an innate feature or
consciousness is an innate feature of
matter i think is what it is correct so
there are there are there are three main
moves that are alternatives to the
emergence move that i take
so
um you got this basic question that
science has somehow dodged for all these
years what is trying and how did it
start
and as a result the culture wars are at
a standstill because
science really doesn't have an answer to
that question and uh fundamentalism does
fundamentalism's answer is mysterion
that's what we call that school of
thought which is there's some special
thing that that causes it it's the
equivalent of that lightning story i
told you before and believe it or not we
have the same thing going on in science
that is you can be a mysterian in
science too
um i would say dawkins is borderline
mysterious
um
he's actually an equivocator and most
mysterians are that means that i mean
sometimes he's talking as if genes
actually are trying to do something
genes are patterns
you know patterns within molecules so
genes are trying to do something but
then he also backtracks on that and says
i don't really mean that i just mean
that it's the equivalent of that and
that explains it so in a way he's a
mysterian but in a way he's also what we
call an eliminativist an eliminativist
says
uh on this question what is trying
and uh and how does it start
wrong question
uh there is no trying
you may try to think that there's trying
but there is no trying um it's a trying
is a figment
and to which we respond figment to whom
because
there's no
you don't trick molecules the atoms are
not tricked they they cannot be deceived
they're not trying to do anything
they're not busy interpreting their
situation to achieve their goals so when
you say that stuff you're talking about
both sides your mouth so i've named two
so far mysterion is you come up with
some black box term that explains it
like god or
a higher power
uh that wants something or whatever
the eliminativism says wrong question
there is no trying you can try to
believe there's trying but there isn't
choose determinism it's another way of
laying out the hypocrisy of that what
the [__] you know
and then the other version of it is it's
a wrong question because everything has
always been trying
and that's what you mentioned as pan
psychism yeah um and no i would say uh
you know i just find it completely bogus
um uh another one of the many dodges we
get to the question makes fine poetry
i'm happy to i'm happy to believe the
whole cosmos is trying to believe uh is
trying to achieve things or whatever you
know i indulge in that kind of romantic
notion that's my note that's my
definition of romance is that the
universe is somehow aligned with us it's
got our back whatever we
it wants whatever we happen to uh
to also want um uh
so
i love that stuff but as escapism
i don't but i no i don't think that's
true i don't think the universe wants
anything i don't think there's anything
outside the universe that wants anything
which is why i'm burdened with the
emergent's question
how did it start because it wasn't there
before the before now if you you know
you could say that you're basically
going
you're going the route of aristotle or
the pet rock
um people of the 1960s jeffrey hear
about the pet rock fad yeah
there's a while when you go out it was a
fad that people were buying pet rocks
and they were just these rocks that came
to you in a nest of of straw in a box so
what i'm saying is um it's like it's a
form of animism
um
uh
much like aristotle saying that a rock
falls to the ground because it wants to
arrive at its proper position that it
belongs further away from god than
humans
a fine notion for his time bless his
pointed head i mean it was good
i wouldn't have come up with it at that
time i i'm impressed but at the same
time no it's not true some things try
and other things don't and we know it
and we should admit it and anybody who
says
anyone who's an eliminativist should put
their money where their mouth is and
start talking like without using any
words that imply motivation will
appetite preference
you know if you think that it's all
chemistry go ahead describe it like that
live it
and if you think that it's all alive
then start taking a little bit better
care of your pet rock and led lights
because
um uh because you know
you know otherwise you're saying you
know it's you're relying on
um
it being counter-intuitive so there's
wishful thinking but i also think that's
dreadful thinking which is um it must be
true because you don't want to believe
it
um and i think both are bogus we want to
believe all sorts of things and that's
irrelevant to whether they're true
so
go ahead
what is the it makes me think that just
like the line between
you know what humans do
acting as if
versus truth
uh uh oh no that's a huge that's a great
question yeah yeah i mean if you know
where i was going with that feel free to
expand because i feel like that is that
is a lot of like where our arguments go
we're arguing over is this true or not
true and a lot of it is kind of not even
trying to prove that it's trying to say
how do humans act as if at this point in
history or or whatever uh yeah so um
so uh
yes that's that's a big deal to me
because actually the last two years i've
been working on a whole other project
that's very much related in
but you might think indirectly um
i called psychoproctology
and i am uh
i'm trying to find an objective a more
objective definition of [__]
um and i'm trying to figure out how to
stop or prevent assholery
without becoming an [__] in the
process um uh and that and once again
i'm an originist that is i have to
explain
a-holes from their origins
if i want to understand what if i want a
good definition of them i can't just
pull it out my butt you know based on
who i don't like uh you know one of the
big questions for me one of the ways i
frame the question of objectivity is
what is a butt head since it can't just
be whoever i happen to butt heads with
you know what's you know so um but
it gets me into this whole i think there
are plenty of nasty animals by our
standards there's plenty of predators
and parasites and all that but being an
a-hole is actually a human thing and it
comes out of having language
which language would make us a really
freaked out animal um
if you compare what a dog could worry
about that night bef uh before going to
bed with what a human could it's we we
got way more real and imaginary
threats and missed opportunities to
consider and way more means to consider
we are extremely anxious and we are also
an extremely evasive
organism
because language also gives us a way to
rationalize dismissing anxious thoughts
so
that's confirmation bias
is basically what it is that is we're
especially anxious and we have good ways
of
avoiding things we have we have skillful
ways of avoiding things that we don't
want to think about
um
uh and confirmation biases
so all organisms have to interact
selectively with their environments they
have to take in food and not
poison
that is like i said earlier energy is
volatile stuff my breakfast could burn
down my house so um
when it's running through my body it is
also degenerating me so i have to i have
to take in the right energy
gradients and not the wrong ones and if
you apply that at the level of language
you get confirmation bias i want to take
in the ideas that regenerate my mojo not
the ideas that degenerate my mojo that's
confirmation bias and by my definition
you know normal people recognize
confirmation bias is a problem they have
to manage and
a-holes
think of confirmation or retreat
confirmation bias as a solution to all
their problems
so
what's going on here related to your
idea so so we will wonder whether we're
talking to someone who is just trying to
win
and um we will wonder whether we should
um
uh humor people
or
tell them what we really think
our best guesses which is there's a huge
difference between honesty and truth
that was completely overlooked in the
last election which is um he tells it
like it is he's honest no that
obviously you can honestly believe
untrue things that's not you know you
can honestly believe things that you
know aren't true we see plenty of
evidence of it i mean it's a kind of
method acting you know we got this from
michael cohen who says after that he
used to be able to put himself in a fit
of complete rage
outrage at someone for something he knew
that the dumb one didn't do you know
they were perfectly good at that sort of
stuff so all the theatrics around this
all the melodrama um all the potential
for falling into what i call
infallibility battles an infattability
battle is either your you turn out to be
right about everything and i turn out to
be wrong about everything or vice versa
it's like a
death match about who's right about
everything it'd be like where if i said
wow you thought that green day album
came out in 96 you don't know anything
do you
you know it's that you can fall into
these things so incredibly easily and
why because
i think what humans are trying to adapt
in three different arenas we have to
adapt to reality that's a long-term goal
it's the same goal that all organisms
have to deal with the one rule is adapt
to reality or die
but we also are primarily and most
pressingly adapting to our own emotions
that is trying to maintain comfort in
our own skin
and in between that we're adapting to
society which can either give us reality
checks or can pander to our need to feel
comfort in our own skin
so i i distinguish these as um
adapting to the likely story that is
this the realistic one
the light the socially liked story the
popular one and the likable story the
story that feels good in my own skin
yeah i i'm thinking about how the self
is expressed in each like you know
all three of these but kind of two of
them and it comes
into reality as the third one or
whatever uh i think have you read much
uh carl jung
uh uh very uh a little enough to know
what he's talking about but not enough
to claim any detailed understanding
right right i'm uh i'm mostly just super
fascinated with him uh he's it's it's
incredibly like it's so
i don't even know if dense is the word
it makes me think about my own
experience so much as i'm reading it or
listening to it that it's like i gotta
pause it sometimes but uh i was thinking
about how um i think in one of his books
i think it was memories dreams and
reflections he describes kind of his
mother and after a while he establishes
um like
her number two personality versus her
number one personality and like who who
she would come out with um in this in
this societal
like
there's basically like two different
sides of ourselves you know our internal
experience and then who we act act out
as in um in our interactions with one
another
and uh
he would just start to point it out like
very blatantly very bluntly in this book
um like oh this is mom as her version
two or as her personality too side of
herself um and it's it's very
fascinating like our internal experience
being
um so different often than our external
experience and right yeah
yeah
also uh i would say that the
our external depends on who we're around
um
yeah i mean i don't know if you've ever
thrown a party where you have friends
coming in from different parts of your
life
and it becomes difficult to know who to
be in that situation because you've been
sort of different with different people
my actually my parallel to it is a
mixing board as i got all these traits
that i'm trying to mix in
in the right blend for
um
for the particular situation i'm in yeah
and i can be too much or too little on
any of them which is fundamental to my
work because a lot of people say you
know always be this way to the max what
i call moral maxing no it's not like
that you can uh my peace of mind comes
from thinking from from being
from wondering whether i'm too much or
too little of any particular trait at
any time that's the closest i'm going to
get the peace of mind is if i'm
wondering equally whether i was too
assertive or not assertive enough yeah
i'm watching both sides of the winding
road i don't want to just try to avoid
one of them so it's like a mixing board
of different qualities that you bring
out in different situations um
and
and so the number one or the social
persona this was a big question during
the enlightenment uh um uh diderot was
interested in this the question of
whether you know
do you wear different masks over your
face or do you are you nothing but masks
um
uh
and
you know do you have an authentic self
and my answer is no i don't um that is
i'm more molten than that uh
um and i can actually explain why also
in terms of origins um that is i could
explain why we would have the impression
that there is a core authentic self but
also why
we would get that by actually by other
means so i mean it's a whole other piece
of the work i do which i could describe
briefly if you wanted it
yeah yeah okay go ahead and describe
briefly and then um actually yeah yeah
go go ahead i want to go okay all right
so
um
language enables me to describe or
detail any model of anything
including myself
so
what happens with language is i can
imagine stepping out of myself and
seeing myself and then describing myself
so
i think of
that this was early work of mine the
four eyes that make up a mind the first
eye is just being it's just um it's eye
to the zeroth power i call it's just uh
it's what we have in common with all
animals we're just being we're operating
on habits now on animals habits main or
plants habits may not be learned in our
case they're learned um and we are in
the habit-making business
that is what consciousness is for it's
for making habits consciousness is not a
computer it's a virtual computer
generator anything that i cannot resolve
ends up rising to consciousness and once
i can resolve it into a habit i will i
will turn it into a habit and stop
thinking about it that's what
consciousness is for from my perspective
and it is largely it's deeply emotive
that is it's triggered by doubt
so i wrote a whole book doubt a user's
guide doubt a natural history um uh
because i think doubt yeah so that's
what rises consciousness that's the
interesting stuff okay but
i to the first either the zero power is
just the running behavior it's my
behavior most of it by habit including
habits of consciousness about how to
turn things into habits but i'll set
that aside i to the first power is my
ability to tell a running unexamined
story about myself so for example i
could say i'm uh
i'm of jewish descent or i'm a people
person or i'm verbal or something like
that
but once so that's me stepping out to
describe myself
but i can keep that going so i could
then go out in order of iteration and
say
i like to think that i'm a people person
um which is me
telling a story about the purse about
the narrator telling the story about my
behavior yeah yeah so that's i squared
and it's actually where science gets
interesting the science is where you
because once you see that you are
telling stories
you uh you can question the stories in a
way you can't if i simply said
what i call second yesing myself i am a
people per i'm a good person
and i've checked with myself and i agree
with myself that i'm a good person so
that would be one thing second guessing
really starts with i squared where i can
say
wait i like to say that i'm a good
person
which raises a question
and then i
ions i mean this was early work when i
was punting uh ad nauseam uh but ions
was where you recognize that for every
story you tell about us yourself another
story could be told about the teller of
that story and that you'll you'll
you know basically you'll bonk you'll
you'll you'll run out of steam
on what are called orders of inference
so i could say i like to say
or i often say
that i like to think that i'm a people
person you know at that point it gets
kind of squirrely but what you do get
from the recognition that you could keep
on telling different stories about
yourself
out layer after layer
is that um
you're guessing who you are
so i have a real problem by now major
red flags when anybody tells me that's
not what i was doing or that's not what
i'm that uh or i'm i'm not uh i'm not a
game player or any of that
self-description i know why we would do
it it would be convenient and it's even
convenient to take someone's word for it
but that talk is walkism the assumption
that what i say about myself is an
accurate description of what's going on
with me
totally bogus to me if someone says i've
got integrity i know that they haven't
given a moment's thought to what
integrity is it just it's just good
bling so they're going to wear it it's
what the other cool kids are wearing so
i mean i've had i've had trump
supporters simply come out of the box
saying i'm a critical thinker and you
can tell they have no idea what critical
thinking is they haven't thought about
it at all but they they want to tell you
they are because why it's ornamentation
i mean it's what the cool kids are
wearing it gives you cred so why not say
it right um
so
so when someone says to me don't tell me
how i feel
they're right i'm not in a position to
tell them what they're that what they
feel they're not they're i'm not an
authority but neither are they
i never i never can tell anybody don't
tell me how i feel like i'm the
authority i mean obviously we know that
there are plenty of people who don't
know what they're feeling what am i
exempt from that of course not no i'm
so you get to have your guess about what
i'm feeling i get to have mine but no
you don't get to you don't get to pull
rank on me just because you're inside
yourself yes you're inside yourself that
makes you both more credible and less
credible yeah right right we get we get
really trapped uh we get trapped in our
self-hood uh in a lot of ways and it
kind of like hinders the ability to uh
uh i don't know solve problems or really
stay on the surface it's a lot of i feel
like so much of your work is probably uh
map versus territory woods versus forest
sort of like we we we missed the point
you know where
we think we're doing this thing yeah
though though i would say
we are trapped in our selfhood
every organism is hustling for it on its
own behalf
um we are all selfish
um in the sense like blueish that is
work to some degree or another we are
going to prioritize ourselves so i have
no use for this version of things that
says uh self selfhood is the problem
get over yourself no i'm very interested
in getting over myself i'm an ironist i
i'm actually i'm an ironist not just by
style or tradition i'm from jewish stock
but because i actually think irony is
the only adaptive response
to
the [__] of switchbacks and
reversals that are
ontologically real that is we know that
there are reversals in the universe and
we are tracking them
so there will be times when we're
heading in one direction because it's
going in that direction and we will want
to track back the other direction and we
will miss
that is there will be times when i uh
prematurely
uh
turn to it change my mind or
postmaturely
change my mind there will be slapstick
what i'm saying is in a world that has
reversals
what's adaptive in one situation will be
maladaptive in another and we're just
guessing we're trying to figure out when
to be there which means that it's going
to be
slapstick there i mean so
yes so this idea that i got an authentic
self or that the solution is to stop
caring about myself i just i have no use
for that stuff anymore and this is after
years of digging buddhism and i lived
for seven years on the world's largest
hippie commune where there was a whole
lot of selflessness now i'm trying to
figure out when to be more
self-assertive and when to be less
self-assertive when to jut my arms as
you you're a dj when the crowded dance
floor
um it's not the the property lines are
not marked out uh everybody would like
the freedom to move wherever um i got to
figure out where to jut out my elbows
and where to tuck them in
[Music]
and and the idea that okay everybody on
the count of three stopping yourself
just forget it it's just unlaughable
it's not gonna it's not gonna happen
i'll become selfless when i die okay
that's what i it's
it's not my calendar but
i i will eventually meld into the
selflessness that's right that's right
later
i was yeah uh
i i like that you brought it into the
world of djing because i was actually
thinking too i i
i'm very fascinated with kind of the
internet and social media and the the
next layer this it gives us this whole
other layer of ego or self that we can
be or say we we are this you know we say
we'll share our highlight reel and a lot
of times we'll get caught up in thinking
that's what our life should look like so
when it doesn't match up to our
highlight reel so to say i love it it
creates quarrels with us and i was also
thinking um so me as me as a dj and me
as a
uh you know as i get older i really try
to try to figure out like how do i
how do i take my creative side and put
it into like this artistry version of
myself like how do i like this so so i
have kind of an alias jacob from the
internet i used to be known as dj kronos
and and i've i've melded it into jacob
from the internet and it's this cool
thing that um and i'm always practicing
i'm not very very good at it but i think
if i continue to do it where i can get
on stage and i kind of have this like
internal all right i'm showing up as
jacob from the internet like i'm not
just jacob and it helps me be an
entertainer it helps me step outside of
myself it helps me like
be more of a goofball tell more jokes
i'm present um and and i look at people
like in in uh
wwe wrestling like the rock there's this
scene in this movie where he kind of
explains where he's he's being polite
and he's talking with these people and
they kind of tick him off and eventually
he's like do you smile with the rock
he's like he gets all into his high up
uh smell with rock is cooking any and
then he explains that's kind of it is me
but it's this amped up version of myself
and he's doing it for entertainment
purposes and and i think about how
we you know common people all have kind
of a version of this uh with our social
media presence and i think i think it
goes over a lot of our heads i think
um i i'm very cognizant of it because i
i i don't want to [__] myself and i
think i have in the past before i really
started studying this selfhood and like
how it makes me act and stuff um so so
what do you what do you think about
social media it's very related uh to uh
kind of a central thesis for me because
i'm trying to figure out
uh
[__] prevention and i think the
fundamental the fundamental tool i have
found for [__] prevention is what
i'll call optimal illusion
or safe escapism or kidding yourself in
ways that help more than harm
so
um
it's not just for our public
presentation a lot of it is for
ourselves we're saying what we need to
hear we're adopting a persona
um and i don't think it's very different
from what we do
um
in a religious context that is we go
into a religious place i was just
noticing the other day that prayer we
never really look at how prayer
uh presents
is a kind of virtual signaling you don't
have to pray out loud but
the prayer is a virtual signal to
yourself as you come across as humble
and supplicating and respectful and all
of that sort of stuff we don't tend to
focus on it that much i've written
articles about god's dogs and blogs and
how
it's related to this which is um we need
more audience than we can get these days
especially because uh what's in shorter
supplies demand that is why because
everybody's out creating now that we
have the social media that is uh you
know and not only this accumulation of
past creativity that is piling up at
this point so um your chances of being
found and
are low but in a way so i when i started
blogging i've now written over a
thousand articles and i have some
audience but when i started i had to
engage in strategic gullibility i had to
pretend that there was an audience that
gave a [__] what i said um
and and i and i love that and i don't
think that's very different from having
a dog or praying to god um just imagine
you got an audience but the thing is we
have to do this stuff carefully
uh i'm interested in safe escapism i'm
saying that entertainment and escapism
are a human necessity
given language we are way too anxious we
could not possibly be realistic all the
time our brains would fry
um it's just not workable um so we need
to take these pit stops of mode where we
get our mojo replenished and they can
take all sorts of forms they can take
the form of virtue signaling online they
can take the form of masturbation i
actually um they can take the form of
belonging to a church where you believe
that you guys have got something
true and and wise and real and that
you're a virtuous and all of that and it
is but in a way i'm dealing with the
same question they were dealing with
with um uh iconoclas the original
iconoclast and there's an issue that
comes up over and over
in
uh in cultural history which i which i
would describe this way is virtual
virtue a virtue or a vice
it's virtual virtue so me posing as
though i'm virtuous
or a stud in bed or i i think of wwe i
think of porn as he as the counterpart
to porn is to uh libido what wwf is to
aggression
um yeah okay so you got so we got all
these mediums that we can do it in uh
that's virtual vice another question is
virtual vice a virtue or a vice but what
i want to say is it's a ver virtual
virtue
is
it's it's a virtue when it motivates
real virtue and it's a vice when it
motivates uh
and it's a substitute for real virtue if
i come out of a movie where i i'll uh
feel aligned with the hero and the poor
person asked me for some money and i say
[__] no i just gave in the theater you
know i just saved all of rwanda you know
so
that's that's that was the issue for uh
abraham it was the issue for the islamic
movement there's a whole thing about
false idols um it was an issue for
luther he brought it up as frequent
communion which is people going to
church and absolving themselves and then
being nasty all week long
they're all dealing with the same thing
uh and um
so
anyway i believe that we have perfect
models for how to engage in optimal
illusion
when i watch a movie
i totally believe it i'm right in it i
am
don cheadle saving rwanda or i am the
hero
but if you tap me on the shoulder i know
for sure that i'm not don cheadle i i
know where i am and when i turn the
thing off i get back to reality it's not
how far out i go into self-indulgence as
dj
kronos or whoever it's whether i know to
come back
and i've been to a trump rally because
seeing fascism up close was on my bucket
list i went to one in tupelo mississippi
i swear the thing was just like
a heavy metal concert people are all
caught it's all cosplay people go out
for a night of entertainment they're
going to chat along with lyrics they're
not thinking about they'd like the
lyrics just because they're badass the
only difference between a trump rally
and uh i don't know the current bans of
of of of that kind of the the
counterpart but you could find them you
know let's say it's like a dj night out
the only difference is that the dj night
out when people are done they get their
cars in their parking lot and they
return to reality
that's the only difference the problem
with the trump rally is they basically
and there's something to it they say i
can get even more juiced on this if i
pretend i found something more real than
reality
and then they kind of keep stuck to that
reality when they if they leave the
concert so to say they leave the valley
and they're still on their phones in the
facebook groups
that's right so so
so you i'm not saying you have to do it
by going to rallies you could do this
online too
and that's the problem so it's not
optimal illusion that's um that's
that's where illusion
gets dangerous we have to continue to
return to reality adapt to reality or
die is the only rule for three you know
3.8 billion years i i don't see us as
having somehow escaped that one so i'm
all into posing i love posing and i also
can say that my life's been lucky
because i've had to do less of it and
then i realized around 50 i actually
could afford to do less of it because i
actually don't need status i have money
from by other means so i actually don't
need status in order to put food on my
table it's an incredibly dumb lucky
situation
and as a result
this is who i am all the time i don't
actually brace myself for a podcast
interview
this is this is who i am
i'm not i i'm not thinking about my
ideas i'm living them there's like you
know it's a kind of seamless
relationship between the ideas and the
practice
and
this is how i talk but that's just the
luxury of not having
to humor people and this relates to love
for you young folk
inc
people often fall into the pattern of
assuming they need a partner
for lots of reasons that they
some of it is hormonal certainty at your
age i couldn't resist
um
some of it is also social pressure or
social encouragement um that's changing
but it's changing in complicated ways
love songs are still uh
uh this about the fantastic urge to
merge and how it feels when you merge
or how bitter you feel in breakup and
how a breakup proves that the other
person was wrong or unkind or
immoral sort of stuff like that so you
still get all that but what i'm noticing
is
um any encumbrance
any obligation to an external source is
going to constrain you
and what you're looking for is
constraints that grow you in the
directions you want to grow but
you can get them lots of different ways
and partnership is a complicated way to
do that for example i was married for 16
and a half years great marriage but we
live in the modern world where there are
lots of lifestyle choices and by
happenstance we sort of diverged to
where
what i thought what was a priority for
me to do was disappointing to her and
vice versa
so we released ourselves from it and we
thank each other for the freedom we got
from it what i want to say is that love
means doing dedicated work to maintain
something you depend on
and you got to be careful what you love
because that is going to constrain your
work it's going to dedicate it's going
to mean that you will be spending
effort doing something keeping up
appearances for example i think there's
an element of that in partnership that
is you have to you have to work hard to
maintain in the other person the sense
of your reliable fascination with them
that's a major obligation it's wonderful
bless it if that's what you want
but to walk into such encumbrances
i think there's something to minimizing
encumbrances
if you are going to pay attention to
reality we also know that people can
fall right off a cliff by minimizing
encumbrances you know you can become uh
you know uh i forget the guy um
yeah you can you know
if if you're unconstrained
you can believe all sorts of crap and
really fall apart so figuring out
wiring up the right external constraints
to support your internal constraints
that is my internal constraints are the
source of my behavior they're what
limits my behavior to what i do and
instead of what i don't do and i have a
bunch of internal constraints and i want
to align them with the external
constraints
that help me grow in the directions
i bet i should grow
they're just bets i could be wrong about
where i should grow but that's a thing
but anyway to be picking up constraints
haphazardly or because other people are
doing it dangerous things to do at 29 i
know a whole lot of people who are 50
and can't believe why the hell did they
choose why they let themselves fall into
that thing
um
there's a poem by philip larkin who was
uh
he says he married her to keep her from
getting away
now she's there all day
and
that's i don't mean that gender specific
i know a bunch of women who said
that who
about who you say she married him to
keep him from getting away now he's
there all day
right
yeah well that's actually very profound
i think that that pokes me personally
too i like it um
i i know we had agreed on an hour do you
have a few more minutes i don't want to
tell you a few more minutes yeah yeah i
i was curious i i really wanted to ask
you um
i i don't know if i if i feel that it is
like the capital t truth if it's it's of
everything i'm very intrigued by the
stoned ape theory and um that realm of
uh
like how language was born i feel like
there's there's a lot of uh overlapping
there so
maybe disregard stone ape theory but
that's totally fine are we talking i
actually don't know the theory is it the
idea that we got into psychedelics and
and pot and all that yeah yeah yeah so
so we start we climbed out of trees and
we started following the the cows and
flipping over the manure and we we ate
it and it was psilocybin and over the
course of a lot of years okay good so
yeah no i have i have some comments
about this oh okay so so because i think
that that language i don't know if i
think this i'm fascinated by the thought
of language perhaps coming out of like
the down the downstream effects of this
but but go on yeah okay so um the
problem with explaining the origins of
language is that we don't have a lot of
data there's a fair amount of stakes in
it that is anytime we're talking about
social behavior and its origins there's
going to be
uh people who care whether it's this way
or that you find a lot of that in
evolutionary psychology for example um
you know it's a touchy subject uh
and on top of that there are too many
theories there's also a problem in in
evolutionary psychology because they're
actually not looking at how
they assume random variation
and if you can explain why something
would be useful if you can say if you
can name a use for something then that's
as good as an explanation natural if
it's useful natural selection would have
generated that's not as much the problem
with the evolution of language but um
here
i'm a stoner i almost never drink
alcohol but i get stoned almost every
night um i i play bass and uh i play
bass in funk jazz soul bands um and sing
and i practice stoned often watching
extended uh run
tv
while i'm doing it i have mixed feelings
about that addiction but mostly by now i
like it or at least i'm settled into it
it's a productive enough time i've
actually gotten my chops together doing
that and i also
i don't have that feeling about getting
stoned i used to be worried that it
would it would injure my brain i don't
find evidence that that it does and my
neuroscience buddy says no it's a it's a
very short-lived drug i've also done all
those psychedelics ayahuasca mushrooms
all that sort of stuff um
uh
i i do not subscribe to that assumption
about it and i can give some reasons why
uh you can get animals stoned and they
don't end up with language um uh and
and uh
that i mean that's that that's a piece
of evidence i'm not saying it's
conclusive um
but
uh deacon this guy i work with he spent
his first 20 years not on the question
of the origins of trying but the origins
of language how it evolved
and um i read his book before he wrote a
book called the symbolic species the
co-evolution of language and brain
um and uh i cried when i first read it
was before i met him before we started
jamming together for 25 years i cried
not because it was moving but because it
was way the [__] over my head no i just
felt like that's totally punked by this
book it was because it was it was the
neuroscience the evolutionary theory the
semiotics of it and what makes language
different from other foreign uh other
forms of signs and inter you know
interpretive relationships where you
know a sign is about something to
someone um
uh
he he does give a more complicated
explanation for
how language would have
evolved um it involves a lot of
neuroscience that was the part that made
me cry because i didn't feel like i
understood that stuff um but
more than that there are these things
that are just so stories and i don't
think the one about the stoned ape holds
up um
as as how you would end up with a what
we symbols are
tokens of a type
so words of a language or symbols of a
mathematical process those are symbols
um and they are held together by social
convention
um
that is dog doesn't mean anything
intrinsically um that it happens to be a
word in our language it's there are
arbitrary marks that are not held as
arbitrary what they refer to as anything
but well it's somewhat arbitrary but
it's it's more specific a dog does limit
possibilities a constraint on
possibility sets that is if you're
playing 20 questions and
and figured out that it was a dog that
narrows possibilities so once again my
work is mostly around constraints but i
would think that it's more social
constraints that would give us
a need for symbols and they wouldn't
start they would start out more as
rituals
and i think they would probably have
more to do with um
with uh
uh
sex actually um uh
not junkyard love but boneyard loves um
but but even then it's highly
speculative and i should say that my
work is far less on how
how language evolved but how language is
different
and what it's like for us mid-sized
mammals
to be adapting under the drunken
influence of language that i described
earlier makes us incredibly prone to bad
trips as we'd be really anxious and
pretty plenty uh prone to escapism
and i also yeah so
i can see i could definitely see a
co-evolution
of mind-altering drugs
and language um but i wouldn't say that
it originated because someone got stoned
and needed words for things i wouldn't
guess that's probably right or
psychedelicized and needed words for
things i i think that that those are
experiences a cat could have on catnip
um and
and yes there are limitations to cat
vocalization systems that would quite
limit i mean so part of what it took for
us to become the primates that speak
is
lucky accidents around our vocal cords
and all of that and
and cognitive changes that enable us to
stop involuntary
sounds
and generate words instead so it takes a
kind of constraint on the
on spontaneous vocalization and we still
have a bunch of spontaneous vocalization
so um
uh moaning and organ orgasm screaming
crying all of that stuff the stuff that
babies do laughing all of that is
involuntary still and the most
interesting part of that for me is
prosody which is
the music that underlies that it's the
emotional carrier way for our words
really interesting stuff cadence and
tonality and that's what all that stuff
is called prosody and it's involuntary i
mean i could fake it i could i could
come you know it's easily faked but we
mostly let it ride automatically
um yeah
yeah so that's
oh man
thanks for uh thanks for indulging me on
that i the language is just so
fascinating um terence mckenna again
with terence mckenna he talked about
he was given this example in one of his
lectures uh about like kind of cadence
into intonality and he he was like uh
what did he do is like sneak sneaker no
good night no he like made up this
little language as an example to to
communicate you don't know what i was
saying i wasn't actually saying anything
but you kind of can connect with the the
tonality of it of like i'm expressing
some sort of emotion or sure which is
which is
and that's a whole lot of the signaling
that we're actually paying attention to
i mean i would see what's what struck me
as i wrote this book about uh
psychoproctology is um
that that's driving not just our
um
our the the tonality but also
it's the prime driver on what we say
there's a there's a conceit out there
that everybody means what they say and
could define every word of what they say
no that's not how we mostly operate with
language we're basically animals praying
and um we happen to bray in language i
mean
i don't mean to
sound cynical or fatalistic about it but
i want to appreciate how much of what we
say ends up
coming about because we we heard
something that we can
ape
uh or parrot
it gets us what we want it becomes a
habit
that we say it
um
it's
it's a it's especially if it works that
means if we can get away with it if it's
if we find a way to say something that
enables us to get our way
it will become our way of saying things
we'll keep on saying it that um and
how do we get our way with it it's by
other people thinking we actually mean
the words
so
um
a lot of what i focus on this actually
makes the psychoproctology work easy to
do because it's extremely non-uh
denominational it's nonpartisan
um
it's a it's a generic habit where you're
simply praying and praying you've gotten
away with praying because people think
you're actually talking about words it's
not at all about what [__] believe i
actually don't think they have beliefs i
i call them trump bots they are
robotically employing
fake trump cards that is
trumped up trump cards so the word trump
both means fake and means beats
everything and of course for an organism
that wants safety and freedom that would
be ideal that you could do anything you
want whatever you want whatever you do
is safe and free um
yeah some some [__] dress up their
beliefs in the lip service window
dressing uh i mean breath they breath
they dress up their ass hollery in some
ornamentation like i'm belong to this
ideology or religion or culture or
whatever but you don't even have to do
that i mean if you're in a if you're in
a relationship where you're being asked
to put out more than you want to
you'll just kind of start snarling and
praying and um pretty soon you'll be an
[__] does that mean that you're an
[__] for uh cause no you can be an
[__] for a cause or not for a cause
the cause doesn't matter it's not at all
about what they claim to believe it's
how they strut it would be a natural
human habit if you could get away with
it to simply bray in words and as long
as people take it you know believe in
civility and honor and and respect and
valuing other people's values and
tolerance and all of that you can get
away with a whole lot of it i believe in
those things whole habitly i believe in
tolerance and listening to people i
believe in that with normal people but i
have to figure out whether i'm dealing
with a normal people because it's
exactly the wrong thing to do with an
[__] it's totally enabling and it's
got us in a very dangerous situation
worldwide and i would say the same thing
if donald trump
was pandering to the left it's got
nothing to do with politics it's simply
you know you know
and i love him that way because actually
you could mistake stalin for a communist
or hitler for an anti-semite no they
were [__] and but trump is really
hard to mistake
for anything but an [__]
um i mean
yes you can if you if you want to
believe in him if you want the perfect
safety and perfect freedom that he
entitles you to
through this formal it's a very simple
system of praying
but um
but no
those don't those beliefs don't matter
we can see that they don't matter
because they
they're
they use them for the preaching they
don't have any interest in practicing
what they preach so it would be true of
any you know it would true stones don't
have to be leftist in his in his
ornamentation doesn't matter it that
doesn't matter we're talking about
playing god being much easier than being
human and that's all you know and you
can play god really easy just by using
words in a certain way that basically is
what i'd call [__] dosing that is
you [__] you don't care what's true
that's not the issue for you you're just
bulldozing through
yeah yeah yeah yeah
oh man fascinating i i i i really
appreciate your explanation uh and i
love where you where you take it i feel
like it's like you're you're kind of
reading what i'm thinking about next and
you're pointing at it already so man
thank you so much um so what what are
you working on right now are you working
on the
is your work on a-holes is that
published that sounds so funny to say
yes and no no it is um so
uh yes and no i just got the proofs for
the hard copy book back from my editor
but i
as my as my last edit on it i recorded
the whole thing as a podcast
or actually a pod class the book i i let
this book sneak up on me by pretending i
was doing it as a class um so i wrote it
kind of as a class um advanced
psychoproctology for beginners um
uh
i'm still working on the title but the
book if anybody wants the book from me
once again i don't need status i don't
need money from this i am i i do like to
have as much audience as i can for the
amount of effort i put into it and also
more than that because i think it's
useful it's not i mean i think we i
think it's the missing piece right now
in the puzzle that is the biggest crisis
we're dealing with is
that we've never quite figured out how
to humbly
humble
people who will say or do anything to
avoid humility
that is that is the big question and if
we don't answer that i think we're as
good as extinct i mean i just don't
think we can i don't think we have the
resources to run out one more
flight of fancy that taken into reality
the way that we that the way this just
keeps on happening so i would love to
get that work out um any so you can find
all of my work you find way too much of
my work simply by just googling my name
uh you'll find all these articles i
write at psychology today i have a
youtube channel on psychoproctology a
youtube channel on origins of life
research or origins of trying research
um
i have a website i'm building that
that's coming along nicely it's at
jeremysherman.com there you'll find my
eight big research questions and the
media page is fully populated with all
sorts of stuff i'm also on facebook
quite reliably because a lot of my i
write most of my essays as memes
i mean i just ended up with a kind of a
bumper sticker mine so i'm i'm i put out
like 10 or 15 memes a day on instagram
and um
and elsewhere so that's a place to find
me if you want um
uh and what am i working on now
all cylinders
that is i'm working on this book right
now today i'm working on an article uh
that i'm submitting to a journal next
week an academic journal on this third
scientific revolution how we bring rigor
to categorization um
uh um
yeah just a lot every every other day or
so i take a walk with terry at where
we're working out a big chunk of his new
work which is on what i'll call
synergenesis which is explaining how
holes come together from parts how
multicellularity or romance happens or
how societies end up with these people
with people
in effect addicted to each other or
elements agents addicted to each other
so how does synergy happen and once
again evolutionary psych or
evolutionary theory in general says well
it happens because it's useful and we're
saying no that doesn't explain how
organisms surrender their autonomy to
become parts of larger whole
so this is terry's current book it's
called falling up he's writing it is
following meaning that i we believe that
a lot of it happens from losing the
ability to do for yourself
because of the available ability of
something else and that would apply yeah
yeah so so that applies to everything
from why humans are addicted to external
sources of vitamin c
because we became encounter we came in
contact with fruit and lost the ability
to generate our own vitamin c after all
you don't have to yeah we don't have to
give you know if i give cats or dogs or
elephants vitamin c you have to give it
to primates because they lost the
ability we know that we have lot we can
trace the dna and yeah we've lost the
ability because we got it from another
source it's also how in a relationship
you can end up losing your ability to be
self-affirming because you're addicted
to some because someone else is
self-affirming you can actually lose
your ability and then when the
relationship ends
you have to regenerate you've got kind
of going cold turf turkey off an
external source of affirmation and you
have to get to back to where you can
regenerate your own mojo so these are
and it also explains why i'm stuck
addicted to grocery stores my ancestors
used to farm but then there were two
ways to get food one was farms and the
other stores and i lost the ability to
farm i could get it back it's different
in different situations but anyway
that's that's a big chunk of our work
these days synergenesis explaining how
synergies happen
yeah oh man that that sounds so great i
uh uh me and a a friend of mine who's a
you know an armchair philosopher uh we
always talk about like we're gonna be
smart old men and and we always talk
about you know one day we're going to be
just like old guys sitting at a
you know drinking tea together and
discussing the nature of reality and i
feel like you guys are living uh my my
hopeful goal from when i'm older that's
i feel lucky i got i have to admit it's
luck i just ended up with a life where i
i happen to stumble into
right opportunities and um
yeah it's not a life for everyone but it
for me the best use of discretionary
time is sitting on the front porch of
the universe speculating about it and us
in it which is what we've been doing and
that's like that's that's a good use of
what life taking notes
we're the only things that can because
we have language we can really take
notes on the whole ball of wax and us in
it um i you know i i love playing music
but i actually like this stuff this
feels this feels good too is what i want
to say yeah it's all play it's all just
such such fun play and you you kind of
get somewhere with it it seems like yeah
that's right and for me so it's it's the
oxymoron not serious play
there's a play within constraints yeah
um uh
because a whole lot i mean i'll talk to
philosophers who will tell me
i had a i got in a debate with one
philosopher and he said well to me it's
all just poetry
i said thank you man
that explains to me i don't you know i
know that if it's all through poetry
then we're not really talking about
what's real
um i'll fuss elsewhere because that you
know i i don't need to try and persuade
you if it's all this poetry right on yo
that's just play
you know if it's all i love poetry i
write dog earl every day almost um but
but no i'm thinking of this as a serious
play trying to get closer and closer to
understanding what
reality can what reality is and uh not
that we'll ever get good at not that
will ever nail it
but but to at least dance you know at
least to at least step on the dance
floor and and check it out you know all
that sort of stuff oh man okay thank you
so much man i really appreciate your
time i really appreciate your
perspective on so many of these things
you definitely i mean just from um me
being introduced for you to you through
the uh the podcast thing uh i'm i'm a
fan already but now i mean just what we
talked about i'm definitely going to
keep diving into your work and and
it's a delight to meet you stay in touch
um i'm i'm i'm east i'm easy i'm around
cool okay and yeah take care and thank
you for having me on your show yeah
of course yeah thank you jeremy we'll be
in touch via email and yeah man take
care and thank you so much again
listeners take care of yourself love
yourself drink some dang water stretch
go outside go for a walk and uh
contemplate the universe from the front
porch
take care
all right
[Music]
with ourselves
knowledge is power
[Music]